uh I have bad news for
you we're gonna
[Laughter]
[Music]
meditate so please get
ready
uh
so because we will finish the Lum roomm
in Koto if we all live that
long uh
we're going to start recording the 100
meditations for the lumm okay and this
is the first one
okay uh so you can say I was
there
okay all
right these are not called lrim
meditations these are called bribery
meditation why we call it bribery
meditation
uh if you joined the
303030 program $1 a
day okay anybody can do that
right uh you get the 100
videos as soon as they are made you get
them like the next day right Tim or
something like that well soon
then if you're grumpy and you don't
support this $1 a
day uh we
will send you the video by United States
Post
Office which takes six six weeks
extra
understand
okay so you know I think you should try
to get the 100 meditations okay and uh
it's just it's a no-brainer it's $1 a
day okay and if everybody helps uh that
means that ACI can be free for forever
for everybody okay and then we don't
have to keep asking you for $10 and you
know kind of waste time right all right
uh you guys ready
yeah so don't forget if you
go in this meditation it'll last for 100
[Music]
years
okay we
call me and my we were four brothers we
were really bad we call silent but
deadly understand you do quiet L and
everybody's
like okay maybe your son does that I
don't know okay you guys ready seriously
ready okay this will be about uh it's
supposed to be half an hour but if Tim
the first one will be 45 I think
okay all
right okay here we go
so please get settled and uh get
comfortable when you meditate in a group
it's better
to try to control yourself
okay clear your
throat okay
small smile on your
face and uh I like to tighten my lower
stomach it helps support your
back try to
relax your
forehead and relax your hands you can
basically do any hand gesture you
like but make sure your hands are
relaxed shoulders back a little
bit shoulders level
your eyes are looking straight ahead but
your eyelids are closed okay so your
eyes
are
looking to the
Horizon uh but your eyelids are closed
if you put your eyes
down your chin will go down
and then you'll get sleepy so keep your
eyes if you open them you're looking
straight
ahead and we're going to count uh 100
breaths uh I know that we usually talk
about 10
breaths uh personally I find 100
breaths uh brings my
mind makes my mind peaceful okay so we
talk a 100
breaths exhale is the first half of the
breath and the inhale is the second half
of the
breath and we'll do a 100
breaths uh you you'll start to think
about something
else and then please bring your mind
back and don't get
all upset and don't be too rough on your
mind treat your mind
gently tell your mind come on we got to
go back to the breath okay so you will
think of other
things and when you catch
yourself come back to your
breath exhale inhale 100 here we
go keep your mouth
sof
e
e e
now on through the 6+ one
preliminaries and the first one
uh please think of someone that you
really
admire uh could be somebody in your
life now it doesn't have to
be a religious person could be
anyone that you really admire and
someone that you would like to be like
that
them maybe it's just a one quality
that you admire maybe not their whole
life
but maybe they have a
special ability to be patient or maybe
they are have a special ability to be
kind so think of a person that you
really admire and invite them to come
and meditate with you it could
be a famous person from the past I I
like to
invite Arya Nar or you know
jetaa or it could even be
somebody you haven't met yet maybe we
all are looking forward to the day when
we meet uh Buddhist
directly and maybe we could ask them to
come now so past present or future
someone you really admire maybe someone
who does not have a certain problem that
you have like if right now if you're
feeling impatient with
somebody then maybe uh try to bring
someone who you know is especially
patient and ask them to meditate with
you uh you can visualize them on the
level of your
forehead uh you can picture them the
size of your
thumb in midair uh in front of your
third
eye in the in the
air uh
maybe one one foot half a meter away
from your head or uh I personally like
to imagine them as a full-size
person sitting together with
me uh in a very relaxed way and like
two friends who are meditating together
I I
enjoy uh being friends with this person
and just meditating together like
friends so get that clear in your mind
and think
about why you admire them and
what is the quality that they
have that you would like to
have e
now imagine that you're making a gift to
this
person I enjoy uh samanta badas
offering and basically you cover the sky
I first I think of the blue
sky and I think of a a day when there's
no clouds in the sky the whole sky is
blue and then I cover the whole sky with
uh I like red roses or flowers cover the
whole sky with beautiful flowers
and offer this to this person just to
honor
them
e e
then we do confession think of some
something you did in the last two three
days that you're not happy about maybe
you got upset at
somebody uh
maybe felt jealous of
someone think
about some negative thing you did in the
last two or three days
and of course we did many negative
things it only takes a few
seconds to make a negative mental
Karma but the goal of this third
preliminary is just
to think of one or two of them and
regret
them and it's it's a good
practice to tell somebody what happened
uh it's very very
healthy if we get in the habit of
telling other people about our
weaknesses or our
mistakes and being honest with other
people
so try to be honest with yourself
and think of something
uh like a bad mental habit
or and tell this person honestly they
are a nice person they're a good
person you could tell them and uh you
will feel
clean so think of something in the last
few days and tell this
person the one you're meditating
with
e e
now tell them something you happy about
something good that you
did um this morning we're meditating
together uh at the end of a retreat at
diamond mountain
and I can feel your meditation is quite
good uh I can feel that you worked hard
this week
uh because I've meditated with so many
people for so many years and um I
think you can be proud of your hard work
this
week and I can tell just from the
meditation that you are you had a good
week and you worked hard and you could
tell this person about your
week and be
happy in a honest way not
prideful be happy that
you made so much progress this
week
e e
the next preliminary is to ask
for
teachings uh I think most of the
teachings we get are from
personal interactions with other
people I think those uh teach us more
than we learn in the class often times
so today and tomorrow the next few days
especially going home from Retreat um
we're going to have
many interactions with other
people we're many of us will be
traveling and
um just make a prayer that in the next
few
days not so much formal teachings
but as we interact with other people as
we have conversations with other
people uh make a
prayer that people teach us some of the
things that people teach us are negative
we see someone acting in a bad
way and we can think I I hope I don't
have to see this again I I hope I don't
do this myself
so ask for
teachings good examples and bad examples
and ask that we
recognize that someone's teaching
us and ask that we learn something from
it
e e
the sixth preliminary we are surrounded
by really good people and I think
sometimes
we we get used to it and we don't notice
them so try to think
of uh some of the good people in your
life
the good examples in your life they
could be personal
friends they could be family members
they could
be public
figures they could be historical
figures
but the people around us are giving us
an example all day every
day and so they are teaching us and ask
your
teachers to stay in your life
pray that you recognize your
teachers and then ask them not to leave
you ask them to
stay e
so after the first six preliminaries we
do our meditation
and today we're going to do a very very
short
meditation it's the
first of the 100 L
meditations and I think to
honor is the first one uh we'll do a
very very important
one so we would like
to in our life we would like to become a
body sappa
and it's a good
goal in a whole
lifetime if we can become a bodh sappa
that would be so
wonderful and we'd be so
happy and we would make other people
happy so
there's to be a bodh
sappa it's very clear very
simple what we have to
do we can become real body
SAA if we have two two different states
of Mind two different
attitudes uh Sam Jong Sam Jong F first
one
uh I would say well the second
one is that we would like to
develop an
understanding of where this world is
coming
from and where all the people are coming
from and where this world is not coming
from and that's the second body CH
ultimate body
CH
understanding cause and effect
understanding mental
seeds understanding that everything
around us is coming from us from how we
treat people
and to get to that
second ultimate bodh
China uh there's
a basic bodh we need to develop
first and that's
love and that's a
concern or that's an
understanding that other people want
have happiness just as much as I do my
whole
day every minute of my
day I'm trying to be happy I'm trying to
make myself happy and that's good and
that's a
great hope in human life to be
happy and the first meditation we'll do
today
is think about one other person
in your life okay could be a friend
could be a
coworker could be anybody family
member choose one person
and the meditation is very short and the
meditation is very
simple do they want to be
happy in the same way I want to be happy
my whole
day I want nice things to happen every
minute of the
day I'm hoping nice things will happen
and now focus on this other
person and just try
to
think are they the same as me do they
they also want to be
happy do they also
hope every moment of the day every
minute are they also hoping to be
happy today every every every minute
is that inside of them also it's inside
of me for
sure but do they also have this inside
of them are they
hoping every minute of
today that good things will happen and
they'll be happy okay just choose
somebody and ask
yourself do they also o want to be happy
every minute
today we'll stay here for a few
minutes and then we'll wrap up the
meditation it's
short but it's extremely powerful and
important and it's something you can do
for the next few weeks if you want to
okay here we go choose one
person
e
e e
then we'll wrap up the meditation we'll
finish the
meditation we did a good
job uh meditation is
short but mental
karma is much more powerful than
physical Karma or verbal
Karma so
just half an hour
of meditation is extremely powerful
Karma it's karma at the center of the
mind which is where the seeds are
created so imagine those
seeds that we created in this
meditation I like to imagine them in the
center of my
mind like little golden seeds in the
mind and then I like to imagine that I'm
sharing those seeds with other people
and I like to imagine that it's like a
golden
sunlight coming out of the center of my
mind and
spreading out past my
body like the Rays of light around the
Buddha
and then spreading out to the world
around
me and I like
to let this golden sunlight
spread uh first in my own
neighborhood and then in the town where
I live everyone is being touched by this
golden sunlight I'm sharing my good
season
and then the state or the province where
I
live everyone's getting a little taste
of the golden sunlight of my good
meditation and then I like to spread it
to the ocean to
the in my country the east coast and the
West
Coast the edge of the country I like to
thank everybody in the whole country
got some golden
sunlight and then I spread it across the
oceans to the other
continents other
countries and then the light bursts out
from this planet and spreads across this
the
space through many many planets and
whole
universe people are touched by the
golden good
seeds of the meditation I did
today and everyone's a little bit
happier
then you can open your eyes
slowly and I like to take a
stretch I like this thing you do with
your hands I don't
know my Chinese friends taught me that
your meditation is quite
good uh I've
been helping people meditate here
for 20
years yeah we had an
anniversary
uh and uh that's one of the best groups
I ever had uh I can feel it I can see it
uh so I guess who I don't know who was
leading meditation here but you must
have done a good
job uh any questions before
we take a what what time do we stop
Timothy 7 7:15 okay any questions
no okay my teacher used to say oh you
know
everything yes Janice venerable
Janice chin
you got to practice her name
trinley
Chinle
tinle okay you could you could call her
tinle she look around like you're
talking to somebody
else thank you for the meditation thank
you for all the teachings this week and
my question is well you know it's really
hard to just focus on one person that
you want to help so so I just kind of
Stack one person in there and fill him
up with a lot of other
people is that okay yeah I think it's
wonderful uh I think um personally I was
doing I wanted to do
three and um I think that's fine yeah um
that's fine my advice in
the there's a meditation
advice that it shouldn't be
so basic that you
get tired or bored you know but it
shouldn't be so busy that you lose your
concentration so it's up to you to
challenge your own mind if it's too
simple you'll get
sleepy and if it's too complicated uh
you you'll lose the emotion uh of
helping them so I I would say you have
to Jud judge your own own balance
Ren uh the guitar string should not be
too tight and not too not too
loose right
Ben
okay
okay yes
Madam we need a box over here
okay thank you gisha for the beautiful
meditation um I have a question about
how seeds are ripening so if every
moment
uh
1605 of the finger snap if every seed
which is ripening creates me and you and
everybody in this uh
room just one seat creates everything
and then next one and the next one is my
my understanding
correct uh it's a good question I I
would say
this
uh we have uh direct
experiences like when I'm looking at
your eyes right now and then we have uh
inferential experiences we have logical
experiences like when I'm looking at you
I know there's people over there I can't
see them right now because I'm looking
at you but I'm having an experience of
them indirectly so I'm looking at you
directly but I'm aware I think those
people did not sneak out to have
breakfast yeah they're still
there so I
can at the same time um my seeds are
creating a direct perception of you and
my seeds in
between are creating inferential or
logical uh perception of them uh so I'm
I'm I'm perceiving a room full of
people but actually I'm just watching
one directly and I'm I'm feeling the
presence of the other people in the room
so that's called the indirect perception
so I'm having a direct perception seeds
are going off to perceive you directly
and then in between those seats there's
other indirect seeds going off and then
I have indirect seeds to to feel that
I'm on this planet and there's many
other people and things like
that those are happening sequentially
those are happening one after another
it's not that they're going on at the
same time I a human mind non Buddha
human mind can only have one instant of
perception millisecond of perception at
at at the same time so I
cannot actually I cannot perceive you
directly and at the same millisecond uh
be aware of them it goes back and forth
the Mind goes goes back and forth uh so
so but but the
direct object and the indirect objects
are created by separa sees and they are
happening
sequentially one after another and it's
very very
fast and
actually whether it's direct or
indirect it's all pictures coming out of
my mind so in that sense there's no
difference between direct and indirect
you see a picture is making you picture
is coming out of my karmic
seat uh and that picture by the way is
unchanging that picture is is in a
moment and so I have picture and then I
have other pictures indirect pictures
but they're all pictures they're all the
same
pictures okay it's very very fast
and U and it's uh
incomplete it's like you make one of
those puzzles with pieces of puzzle and
you're always making one part and then
the other part's not there and then you
fill in that part and this part's not
here and so actually our perception is
very scattered you know that's human
human being when you become a Buddha
it's all
unified yeah
stop trowing things all right okay
yeah
Tracy good morning thank you for that
beautiful
meditation um my question is if a seed
never touches the
tree um when it comes to
correlations if I want to get this I'm
going to do that well how does that ever
touch where I'm going with that so can
you help me to understand these
correlations so my question is why like
how does that happen gisha yeah good
good
question H certain questions are are a
logical certain questions are a
logical consequence from thinking
correctly you see what I mean you should
have certain questions after a while and
if you don't have them it means you
aren't
thinking you see what I mean so I'm
happy when people ask a certain question
I know they're
thinking uh if if you didn't think of
this question you should be uh is what I
mean to say
so uh if you have a
pen and you are writing on a piece of
paper
uh there's a strong strong feeling of
your ignorance or misunderstanding by
the way I don't like to call it
ignorance nowadays I I would call it
misunderstanding it has to be
mistaken uh ignorance can imply lack of
knowledge misunderstanding means crooked
knowledge and that it's crooked
knowledge okay
so piece of
paper and you're right with a
pen and it looks like the pen is making
the the marks on the paper and and and
then you can
think ignorantly sorry misunderstanding
L uh you can think that the pen is
making the marks on the paper and that's
a mistake to think that is a mistake
okay and it's
natural to think that and because it's
natural you stay in SAR be because you
think the
pen writes on the
paper you suffer you stay in this world
suffering because you believe that you
think cause and effect
means the pen ink is is making the mark
on the paper okay and you think that's
causing effect
therefore you try to get more pens in
your life you you work for money to get
more pens you think this cause an effect
okay but on the what's really
happening is uh pen seeds are opening
pen seed pen seed pen seed pen seed
paper seed paper seed paper seed paper
seed writing writing writing writing
your mind is create your seeds are
creating the
paper then your seed creates a hand then
your seed creates a pen then your seed
creates letters coming out of the pen
but the pen does not make the letters
the pen does not make the letters and
that's very difficult to to understand
it's very difficult to appreciate so
there is cause and effect when you're
writing on a piece of paper but none of
it is between the pen and the
paper it's it's all your seeds in your
mind laying things down there you know
one after another in in a in an apparent
cause and effect which is not a cause
and effect trying to make the apparent
cause and effect
happen over and over and over is the
frustration of sansara that is sansara
that is sansara trying to collect more
pens trying to make sure other people
don't get the pants you know that's
sansara and then it's all sansara is
defeated by understanding pictures are
coming out one after another it's all
cause and effect from the mind so in the
case of a seed and a
tree there is a seed there is a seed
there is a seed there is water there is
sunlight there is
fertilizer and then suddenly a tree
appears but it's not coming out of the
seed the seed is coming out of your
mental pictures mental picture seed
mental picture seed mental picture seed
mental picture seed mental picture tree
mental picture treat meal the cause and
effect is all
here the the seed cannot
create the tree it's not physically
possible okay uh because as you
said by the time the tree is there the
seed is gone so they never touch they
never make contact the pen tip never
touches the
paper okay never and and the seed by
definition a seed cannot make contact
with a
tree a tree can never be coming from a
seed it's
impossible uh so something else has to
be going on which means your mind
creates seed your mind creates seed your
mind creates seed your mind creates tree
why then
gesla I can see what Angelo's thinking
already
uh why then do we bother to plant seeds
in the spring if we want trees you know
and those are called patterns okay
they're are karmic patterns there are
patterns to sansara the seeds don't
cause the plants but if you don't plant
the seeds the plants won't
grow because it's a pattern it's a it's
a karmic pattern okay there there are
always in this
world normally there are seeds physical
seeds are planted before the tree comes
up and and those are karmic patterns
those are patter s that that hold true
most of the time until you get more
advanced okay and you can make trees
open without seats okay
cool
okay
uh I'm supposed to fundraise I'm under
big pressure to fundraise okay L one
more he wait wait wait
microphone by the way this is almond
milk okay you take a handful of almonds
soak them overnight they get
fat then they're
ready uh rinse off the
water uh throw them in a blender add
Lots add a little water blend it and it
will be smooth and then add more water
blend that and it'll be smooth then
throw in uh strawberries okay
and
uh and make two of
them and
uh I I generally I don't eat until noon
but I have two of these two or three of
these and
um and then uh you don't gain weight
they don't have any carbohydrates the
the almonds don't have any and the
strawberries don't have any then you
can so you don't you can be you can fit
in your clothes permanently
okay and it's so simple it's so duh you
know duh okay so it's a carbohydrate
thing so you it and it's healthy and
it's cheap and I can save time and I
don't have to cook and okay just
suggestion okay uh thank you Gesa uh
just for uh the second question upon the
uh the just now the question is life for
physical seed is understandable but for
mental SE how about how about them is it
the same pattern or so for the
correlations can we how can we
fix yeah good it's a good question thank
you uh her basic question is uh I can
appreciate the Tracy
answer about pine trees and pine tree
seeds I understand that but does that
apply to mental seeds is it the same and
the answer is yes it's the same uh a
mental seed does not produce a mental
picture uh the mental picture is not
necessarily coming out of the seed you
perceive it coming out of the seed
because you've always done that and I'll
give you an example from the mind only
school okay and this is why you should
come to the mixed nuts translation
classes they're
free uh it's the wisdom of 2,000
years you know we Ed them to be
convenient for you they're not
convenient for
me uh and
um if you keep going to those classes
all the questions will be answered okay
all the questions you ever had will be
answered uh
so in the mind only school they say when
you look at a a pink color
uh you are actually you are just looking
at a pink color in your Storehouse
Consciousness Al visana you're
watching seeds open in your own mind
there's no pink outside outside of you
everything is in your mind that's mind
only school okay it's not middleway
school but it's useful so they believe
that you are just watching part of your
own mind you
there's no Cup this far away from gila's
head my eyes over here the the colors
over there then there's a big question
in the mind only
school okay so
actually when I see pink
color I'm actually just watching part of
my own mind in the mind only school I'm
just watching part of my own mind then
the question comes up
why do I feel like it's outside why do I
feel like that why does it feel like
it's half a meter sorry one meter away
why does it feel like it's one meter you
know where does that come from and the
mind only School says you have special
seeds from the past that create the
illusion of distance that outside there
there's an illusion of outside that
there's a separate
seed in your mind that's creating the
feeling that the color is outside then
the big question then your question
comes up Ella's
question uh where did that seat start
and the answer is it
didn't okay what's that mean it means
look that thing's been going on forever
that se's been going on forever okay you
you can't point to the first day in your
past
life when you thought the cup was
outside you cannot point to it because
that had to have a seed to cause it so
so in your past life you thought the cup
was outside why because the line before
that you thought the cup was on the
outside why because the
cut you know and then
westerners non- Buddhists they have
trouble with that they're like that's
weird you know seed comes from an old
seed and that came from an old old seed
and that came from an old old old seed
and that's weird and then you know a
real Buddhist say no you're weird you
know it's weird to think there was a
beginning that's weird if you think
about
it it's it's dumb to think there was a
beginning because then nothing something
came from nothing nothing comes from
nothing nothing ever could so somewhere
in my life or
childhood I must have done
something
good that's an Old English song uh Sound
of Music right Sound of Music yeah
anyway
that's all so yeah that's the came from
the Imp the the
impression that mental seed start and
then create a mental
picture and and the impression that
that's a pattern and that pattern has
always been and it's I'm not avoiding
the question when I say it's always been
that way okay like it's the same thing
your mom said you know why can't I have
candy all
time because that's the way it
is okay